[Music] today on Polar Ice creamy we are going
to look at dondurma which is Turkish ice cream,
the stretchy stuff that you see vendors
play around with elsewhere on the internet,
so come with me on this really
weird ice cream journey [Music]
So why is it weird? it's not really weird it's
just the internet seems to do a lot of things
right and wrong that's I mean we're all here to
learn and be entertained but this is a really
difficult one because Western countries don't have
this style of ice cream or haven't until recently
when certain parts of the world have had Turkish
ice cream introduced to them. Ontario,CA has got
some, London, UK 's got it, I'm sure there's you
know something in in the US as well and what makes
Turkish ice cream unique is its stretchiness.
It has a very unique texture and what we're
going to do today, which is a part one because
there's a lot to talk about in this subject,
is we're going to talk a little bit about
the history of this Turkish ice cream,
what we're going to use to make it,
what we're not going to use to make it,
what on earth this stuff is and probably
drink some of this at the same time.
Turkish ice cream also known as dondurma which
means "ice cream" or "freezing" depending on
which part of Turkey you come from. Tt has
a rich history that dates back centuries,
its origins can be traced to the time of
the Otoman Empire but the exact details
of its creation are not well documented,
but it is believed to have been influenced
by Persian and Arab ice cream Traditions.
Traditionally, Turkish ice cream is made
using a combination of milk sugar and Salep which
is a flour made from the root of wild orchids,
salep gives Turkish ice cream a unique texture
and elasticity. The mixture is then flavored
with various ingredients such as mastic resin or
rose water which can add a very distinct taste.
Ice cream vendors known as dondurmaki often
perform entertaining tricks and stunts while
serving the ice cream itself, they use long
paddles to stretch and pull the ice cream
creating a show for their customers. This playful
interaction has become a characteristic feature of
Turkish ice cream culture. So now we have a bit
of history or background of Turkish ice cream,
let's talk about a few things. One, this here
is not the Orchid root salep... I'm going to
absolutely muller some of the pronunciations in
this video and the next which is the part two
video by the way so apologies if you're in Turkey,
i'm doing my best. This is a starch pudding drink
which is served in the winter and is not the
Salep Orchid Root Powder that you would use in the
dondurma. This is mastic resin I managed to get
this in a Mediterranean supermarket in Calgary,
this actually came from the Greek section
so there's a lot of crossover between Greece
and Turkey relating to some of these ingredients,
mastic and salep powder itself. This is gold dust,
this is the salep powder, this came from Turkey.
I have a lot of Turkish followers and subscribers
on this channel so thank you for, you know
who you are, that sent me this it's not easy
to get hold of and if you can, it is incredibly
expensive so we're very lucky to have this here
today. Turkish coffee, I'm not going to go into
too much detail about Turkish coffee cuz this
isn't a coffee channel but maybe in the next
video in the part two I'll talk a little bit
more detail about Turkish coffee and why
it's different because Turkish coffee is
often served with something sweet on the side
usually Turkish delight or another sweet treat
but maybe we'll talk about that in part two
so let's get all this stuff out of the way.
So you look online ,you want to make Turkish ice
cream there are a million different recipes trying
to imitate that stretchiness, trying to imitate
that really unique thing that salep powder does.
I've tried a lot of them over the last 4 or
5 months. I found one alternative recipe that
uses a combination of stabilizers which we're
going to talk about in part two. In part one
we're going to make make traditional Turkish
ice cream so let's get on and make Turkish
ice cream using salep root powder (so Orchid
root powder ) and mastic resin to flavor it.
We've got everything here we need, we
are going to need 600g of goat milk,
200g of cream, 150g of sugar, 3g of ground mastic
and 15g of our salep ground Turkish Orchid root.
So one of the Channel's followers gave me
some great background on how his mom and
grandmother used to make this for him and
he said that they didn't heat this at all
so that's what we're going to do, straight from
the horse's mouth so to speak, let's just let's
just roll with it. So we're going to do this all
in real time so what what do we need goat's milk
which is incredibly expensive, I don't even know
what this I don't know what goat's milk tastes
like tastes just like normal milk, it's quite
high fat. I think it's tasty high fat how how much
fat is there per one cup for God's sake um 9g of
fat so you know 3% it's not too high it's normal
Anyway enough talking, 600g of goat milk,
200g of cream, come on 150g of sugar. What
I'm going to do is take that off and I'm
going to put the remaining 15g in here,
mastic and salep we can do 15g in here and
finally we need 3g of our ground mastic.
okay how much is in this one
Okay right we're going to grind this up
we're going to put all of that in there
and just put it together and apparently
that stops the mastic going too sticky
because it's basically just gum and mastic
has been chewed as a chewing gum for years,
I mean you know a seriously long time. Put this
in here and we are going to whisk it for 2 minutes
We want to make sure that that sugar is dissolved
and there's no Powder so we're going to run your
spoon along the bottom of the bowl use the
back of the spoon against the side that
will tell you if there's sugar undisolved,
anyway I think we got it all, tastes nice.
Right we are now going to cover that and
put that in a fridge for 1 hour. Okay
ice cream out the freezer tiny whisk well
it's definitely thickened let's get this
in here right with the last in a normal ice
cream you probably keep going for another 5
minutes or something like that on the
churn but cuz this is something a bit
different we're at this kind of stage look
it's keeping it shape and I can hear the
machine starting to or the ice cream start to
thicken up by the change in the tone of the
machine so we're on to the next stage. Got my
stand mixer in the freezer ,I've got the bowl
the bowl is a ceramic bowl, what we're
going to do is we're going to get that
out and I've got the the beater in the freezer
as well cuz it's made of metal and we're going
to transfer this almost frozen or partly frozen
ice cream into that and we're going to whip it,
we're going to beat it for 2 minutes all right so
let's turn that off and get everything else ready.
I mean it's winter now here in Canada so
it's -17°c it was colder than that this
morning, let's get ready actually I'll
probably put that on after wish me luck
[Music]
move that out the way make sure it doesn't fall
off, only so many
plugs
and let's
get my phone and show you what I can
see
interesting right, well there we go let's get this
into our container and get it in the freezer.
[Music]
So something to remember is that the ice
cream that the vendors sell and serve in
these you know Turkish ice cream parlor it
isn't at the same temperature as the ice
cream straight out of your freezer much in
the same way that gelato is served slightly
warmer that's why it's a little bit softer a
little bit more pliable. So what I've done is,
this has come out of freezer about 15
minutes and I'm trying to recreate the
the pounding that they do with these these uh
um tools you know they're like a it's like,
um, it's like a mallet if you will they beat
the ice cream to soften it and to increase the
stretchiness so I don't have one of those I'm
sure you don't either. So you get it to a point
where it's just starting to become malleable and
just work it work it for about five minutes and
then what we'll do is we'll I mean I can
see it's already here we go what have we
got stretchy ice
cream so what do they do they serve it up in an
ice cream cone let's get one shall we Walmart
special this is uh look at it it gets to the
right temperature and suddenly it starts to make
sense difficult to do a thumbnail
with this stuff right first things
first I think you'll agree we
we've pretty much nailed the the
stretchiness look at [Music] that so
indicative of serving temperature I don't know,
likely somewhere around the -10°C something
likle that will help activate the mastic which
will make the stretchy the salep or however you
want to pronounce it that is is the stabilizer
you can you can taste the rootiness of
it but it's certainly not a bad flavor,
it's got notes of cinnamon kind of like a touch of
vanilla in there. Texture wise, It's kind of what
you'd expect it's a little bit gummy, it's quite
smooth, there's not a lot of ice crystals in there
which is good. I think if you added something,
you know like vanilla or pistachio or something,
like that to this would be it' be really nice.
So Turkish ice cream, made..... I'm not going to
say made the traditional way but I made it
with traditional ingredients and next week
we're going to make a modernist version of
this without salep and mastic so if you want
to see how we get on with that, stick around
like and subscribe and I'll see you next week.